Guide to the Youth Document Durham and Durham Works Project Records, 1995-2008 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Youth Document Durham and Durham Works Project records 1995-2008 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Center for Documentary Studies
45.5 linear feet Extent: Approximately 10,085 Items
Youth Document Durham and Durham Works were programs sponsored by Duke University and the Center for Documentary Studies that brought together young people ages 12–16 from diverse Durham communities to document their lives, local history, and contemporary social issues through photography, oral history, and narrative writing. The Youth Document Durham and Durham Works project records span the years 1995-2008 and document the process of training young people in Durham, North Carolina schools to use photography and other arts, oral histories, and writing to record the history and members of their communities and the local issues affecting the students' lives. Many of the students are African American or Hispanic and their topics often highlight social conditions and race relations in African American and Hispanic communities in Durham neighborhoods and in a few other locations, including South Carolina. Topics explored by participants, both interviewers and interviewees, include crime, food cultures, jobs and education, music, racism, technology, teen violence, work cultures, and tobacco cultivation and its social context. The bulk of the collection is made up of hundreds of oral interviews conducted by junior high and high school students with community members, documented through audiocassette recordings, photographs, writings, and some transcripts, but there are also many program publications, project curricula, and administrative records for the program from its beginnings through 2008. There is also a database created by Center for Documentary Studies staff that records the complete information for each interview, including descriptive notes on certain interviews. This data also contains restricted information. For access to this database, please consult with a reference archivist. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
RL.01428
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted. Interview folders with no accompanying release forms are closed to research for 50 years from the date of creation. These folder numbers are specified in the database. Also, original audiovisual materials are closed to use.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Some use copies are available in the collection. Otherwise, Technical Services staff need to produce use copies before contents can be accessed.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Youth Document Durham and Durham Works Project Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2009 and 2011.
Historical Note
Part of the larger Community Programs department in the Center for Documentary Studies, "Youth Document Durham" was a summer program that brought together young people, ages 12–16, from diverse Durham and surrounding communities to document their lives, local history, and contemporary social issues through photography, oral history, and narrative writing. Many of the students are African American or Hispanic and their topics often highlight social conditions and race relations in African American and Hispanic communities in their neighborhoods. Topics explored by participants, both interviewers and interviewees, include crime, food cultures, jobs and education, music, racism, technology, teen violence, work cultures, and tobacco cultivation and its social context.
For four intensive weeks, students learned the skills to create photographic bodies of work with a manual camera, the techniques required to process film and develop prints, interviewing skills, computer-based audio editing, and how to write narration reflecting their experiences. They also made decisions about how they would explore their group's topic; they chose who they might want to interview, where and what they would photograph, and what project or event might reflect their work so that they could then share their ideas, stories, and photographs with the larger community. The program produced public forums, web sites, exhibits, and publications. The Youth Document Durham program received funding support from the City of Durham and the Triangle Community Foundation, through the Quintiles Give Back Fund and the Fund for Women and Girls of Durham. Originally called "Community Stories," it is sometimes referred to it in this way in the collection.
Also part of Community Programs, Durham Works was an after-school career exploration program that encouraged young people to focus on questions about education, jobs, and the world of work. Using cameras and tape recorders, middle-school students met with community members who were working in jobs that the young people found intriguing and appealing. Their documentary work was presented back to the community in various ways, including exhibits, videos, art installations, and posters.
Collection Overview
The Youth Document Durham and Durham Works program records span the years 1995-2008 and document the process of training young people in Durham, North Carolina schools to use photography and other arts, oral histories, and writing to record the histories and members of their communities and the local issues affecting the students' lives. Although the vast majority of the projects focus on Durham, there is also one project based in South Carolina. Topics explored by participants, both interviewers and interviewees, include crime, food cultures, jobs and education, music, racism, technology, teen violence, work cultures, and tobacco cultivation and its social context. The collection is divided into four series: Interviews, Photographic Material, Project Files, and Additions.
The bulk of the collection is made up of hundreds of interviews conducted by junior high and high school students with community members, but there are also many program publications, project curricula, and administrative records for those years. The contents of each series is described in full below. There is also a Community Stories database that houses the complete information for each interview, including descriptive notes on certain interviews, and restricted information. For access to this database, please consult with a reference archivist.
The Interviews Series forms the bulk of the collection, and houses the materials generated by the student projects. Each session was organized around a topic which usually would be repeated in subsequent years, such as Durham Works or Old Five Points. Folders usually house one set of interviews conducted by one or more students, and contents typically consist of one or more cassette tapes of the oral interviews, consent forms and other documentation about the interviewees, and writings by the students that came out of their experiences as interviewers. Some interviews have been transcribed. Original audiovisual materials are closed to use; viewing or listening copies need to be made before contents can be accessed. Folders are arranged in number order as assigned by Center for Documentary Studies Staff; they are not in chronological order. An alternate listing at the end of this collection inventory groups boxes by project title rather than folder number order.
In addition to oral histories and writings, the students also produced many images of their subjects and their communities. Photographic prints and negatives of their work are housed in the Photographic Materials Series. Students also produced poems and drawings, and these are chiefly found in the Project Files Series.
Supporting program materials - curriculum guides, notes on staff meetings, staff guidelines, assessments of outcomes - are found in the Project Files Series. Also housed here are additional photographic images, mostly of the project students and staff, CDs with final projects, and the many publications that came out of the Center for Documentary Studies program. These booklets contain mostly interview transcriptions but also include photographs, drawings, annotations, and poetry. Also included is a retrospective collection of Youth Document Durham participant photos and essays, edited by Hong-An Truong and published in 2005.
Later accessions to the collections are found in the Additions Series. These items consist of audiovisual materials, photographs, and some printed materials. In addition to the Youth Document Durham project, related projects included in the Additions series are the Youth Treatment Court, which seems to have been a division of Youth Document Durham, and the Connect Program, which included projects from Old Five Points as well as special group projects for youth.
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
[Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.]
Collection Arrangement
Organized into four series: Interviews, Photographic Material, Project Files, and Additions. The original arrangement of the interview files is in folder number order as assigned by the Center staff rather than by project. For easier access, an Alternate Listing by Project Title also appears at the end of this inventory.
Subject Headings
African Americans -- North Carolina -- Durham -- Social conditions; African American teenagers -- North Carolina --Durham -- Social conditions; Civil rights -- North Carolina -- History; Documentary photography -- Durham (N.C.); Documentary photography -- North Carolina; Documentary photography -- Teaching and education; Hispanic Americans -- North Carolina -- Durham -- Social conditions; Hispanic teenagers -- North Carolina -- Durham -- Social conditions; North Carolina -- Race relations; Secondary education -- Programs -- North Carolina; Teenagers -- North Carolina; Teenagers' art -- North Carolina; Youth programs -- North Carolina; Durham (N.C.) -- History -- 20th century; Durham (N.C.) -- Social conditions; Durham (N.C.) -- Pictorial works; Durham (N.C.) -- Social life and customs; North Carolina -- Pictorial works; North Carolina -- Social conditions; South Carolina -- Social conditions; South Carolina -- Social life and customs; Audiocassettes; CD-Rs; Contact sheets; DVDs; Electronic documents; Negatives; Oral histories (document genre); Photographs; Slides (photographs); Duke University. Center for Documentary Studies; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
Related Material
Youth Document Durham is one part of a larger Community Programs department in the Center for Documentary Studies. Other Community Programs include:
Literacy Through Photography Records, 1990-2000
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Durham Traditional Arts Survey Project Records, 2000-2002
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Neighborhood Project Records
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Youth Noise Network Records
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Contents of Collection
- Interviews Series, 1995-2008 and undated, (53 boxes)
  Folders house materials from interviews conducted by students with community members. The interviews focused on specific program themes relevant to the communities being studied. The documentary project "Community Stories" describes neighborhood communities mainly in Durham, North Carolina but also in other cities including Wilson, North Carolina and Summerton, South Carolina. The interviews were recorded on audiocassette tapes which are sometimes but not always accompanied by typed or hand-written transcriptions and student notes. The folder titles and database information from which other information was taken sometimes do not reveal the project name; when known, the project appears first.
  The interview materials are often but not always accompanied by an interview agreement form, which the interviewees and interviewers have both signed to allow for the release of their interviews for public use. For interviews with no release forms, researchers are responsible for obtaining permissions to publish.
  [Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.]
  - [Note: Folders 1-34 could not be located in the CDS at the time of transfer.] (Box 1)
  - Tobacco Talk. Taborn, Arthur. Durham. Tobacco worker. 1998 July 23 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Craig, Sharon. Durham. Day Care Center Employee. 1998 July 30 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Quick, Charles. Durham. Police Officer at Duke University. 1998 July 26 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Tobacco Talk. Bailey, Emma. Durham. Nanny. 1998 July 27 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Tobacco Talk. Scarlett, Bonita. Durham. Beautician. 1998 July 18 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Tobacco Talk. Warren, Kirk, Sr. Durham, West End. Housekeeper. 1998 July 27 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Stitt, Cecilia. Durham. 1998 July 26 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Tobacco Talk. Clark, Jonnie. Durham. 1998 July 14 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Sounds of the City. Brightleaf Square, Bus Terminal, South Square Mall, Wellspring, and West Point on the Eno. 2000 June 13-15, 21 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    No documentation in file, 4 interview tapes: Nicholas Spivey, Juan Dian, Caitlin Angell, Stanley Bass; Nicholas Spivey, Brittny Gill, Stanley Bass; Maura and Kelly, Brittny Gill; Juard Deshaun.
  - Community Stories. Mrs. Walker. 1999 July 9[no documentation in file, single interview tape only] (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Community Stories. Harris, Ethel.[no documentation in file, single interview tape only] (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Community Stories. Langley, Vernon. (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Community Stories. Canady, Delphine. (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Community Stories. Beamon, Gloria. (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Community Stories. Gordon, Yolanda. (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Community Stories. Stewart, Ed. 1998 July 28 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Community Stories. Bonds, Marlynda. Durham. Social Worker. 1998 July 8 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Hornsby, Angela. (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Community Stories. Primpey, Leroy. 1998 June 26 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Community Stories. Myer, Victoria. 2000 June 22 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Community Stories. Marsellas, Kim. Journalist. 2000 June 22 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Community Stories. Evans, Bobbie. 2000 June 16 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Community Stories. Johnson, Elizabeth. Officer in Durham Police Force. 1998 July 28 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Community Stories. Tsai, Kelly. (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Blind, Roy. 1998 June 29 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Lapinski, Terri. Figure Skater. (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Crest Street. Calhoun, Michael. Durham,Crest Street. 1998 Apr. 7 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Tobacco Talk. Marks, Bertha. Durham. Health Center Employee. 1998 July 26 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Crest Street. Patterson, Willie. Durham, Crest Street. 1997 Sept. 10 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Tobacco Talk. Headen, Sandra. Public Health Educator. (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Scurlock, Ila. Durham. (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Old Five Points. Holloway, Emmer. Durham. 1992 July 24 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Brown, Cynthia. Durham. 1998 July 27 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Bell, William. Durham. Engineer. 1998 July 29 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Page, Michael. Durham. Church Administrator. 1998 July 30 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Behind the Veil. Lawson, Henry. Summerton, S.C. 1995 July 11 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Mercy Hospital. Coleman, Nilla. Wilson. 1996 July 25 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Richardson, Ida. Summerton, S.C. 1996 June 25 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - West End. Ting, Luela. Durham, West End. 1997 July 7 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Old Five Points. Sherald-Campbell, Olivia. Durham. 1997 July 10 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Old Five Points. Brockington, Pattie. Durham. 1997 July 3 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Atwater, Will. Carrboro. 1998 July 29 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Stover, Darrell. Cary. 1998 July 14 (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Marshall, Andre. Durham. 1998 July 10 (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - Parrish, Theodore. Chapel Hill. 1998 July 15 (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Old Five Points. Dickey, Christopher. Durham. 1998 July 27 (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Smith, Lenora. Durham. Project Coordinator at NECD/PAC.1998 (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Payton, Shirley. Durham Director of NECD Smart Start at Duke University. 1998 July 14 (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - Constantine, Julia. Manning. Day Care Operator. 1996 July 6 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Summerton, S.C. Choice, Dorothy. Summerton, S.C. Teacher. (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - Brunson, Harold. Columbia. Teacher, Principal, Coach. 1996 June 20 (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - Gaymon, Rufus. Manning. Reverend. 1996 July 16 (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - Bethune, Thelmer. Pinewood. Farmer. 1996 July 5 (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - Herrington, Edna. Sumter. Teacher. 1996 July 21 (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - Gist, Suzanne. Manning. 1996 July 7 (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - Solomon, Ruth. Summerton, S.C. Media Specialist Assistant. 1996 June 20 (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - Old Five Points. Langley, Angela. Durham. Rehabilitation Counselor, City Council Representative. 1998 July 27 (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - Old Five Points. McLean, Raymond. Durham. Manager at Winn Dixie, Minister. 1998 July 29 (Box 5, Folder 92)
  - Old Five Points. Jones, Michael. Durham, Northeast Central Durham. Insurance Claims Adjustor, Mortician. 1998 July 29 (Box 5, Folder 93)
  - Old Five Points. Fisher, Iris. Durham. Cafeteria Manager. 1998 July 30 (Box 5, Folder 94)
  - Old Five Points. Everette, Arthur. Durham Minister. 1998 July 29 (Box 6, Folder 95)
  - Old Five Points. Kenan, Anne. Durham 1998 July 16 (Box 6, Folder 96)
  - Old Five Points. Stewart, Ed. Durham, North Durham? Teacher, Activist. 1998 July 28 (Box 6, Folder 97)
  - Old Five Points?. White, Nathaniel, Sr. Durham. Printer. 1998 July 28 (Box 6, Folder 98)
  - Mercy Hospital. Simon, Woodrow and Mary Etta. Wilson. 1996 July 23 (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - Simmons, James. Summerton, S.C. 1996 July 4 (Box 6, Folder 100)
  - Nelson, Joyce. Summerton, S.C. Cook. 1996 June 27 (Box 6, Folder 101)
  - Durham's West End. Lewis, Sarah. Durham, West End. 1997 July 24 (Box 6, Folder 102)
  - Durham's West End. Morman, Elmaire. Durham, West End. 1997 July 17 (Box 6, Folder 103)
  - Mercy Hospital. Banks, Connie. Wilson. Teacher. 1996 June 26 (Box 7, Folder 104)
  - Mercy Hospital. Langston, Mary. Wilson. Nursing Assistant, Secretary. 1996 July 11 (Box 7, Folder 105)
  - Mercy Hospital. May, Nellie. Wilson. Health Aide for Social Services. 1996 July 23 (Box 7, Folder 106)
  - Mercy Hospital. Gibson, Olivia. Wilson. 1996 June 24 (Box 7, Folder 107)
  - Smith, Estell. Summerton, S.C. Farmer, Housewife. 1996 June 28 (Box 7, Folder 108)
  - Green, Antonio. Summerton, S.C. Teacher. 1996 July 2 (Box 7, Folder 109)
  - Mercy Hospital. McKinney, Stanley. Wilson. 1996 July 23 (Box 7, Folder 110)
  - Mercy Hospital. Coble, Maurice. 1996 June 26 (Box 7, Folder 111)
  - Summerton, S.C. Dow, Carolyn. Pinewood. 1997 July 15 (Box 8, Folder 112)
  - Mercy Hospital. Crooms, Bobby. Wilson. Janitor. 1996 July 30 (Box 8, Folder 113)
  - Mercy Hospital. Green, Frances. Wilson. Nurse. 1996 Aug. 9 (Box 8, Folder 114)
  - Mercy Hospital. Raynor, Lessie. Wilson. Nursing Assistant. 1996 Aug. 1 (Box 8, Folder 115)
  - Mercy Hospital. James, Helen. Goldsboro. Nurse. 1996 July 30 (Box 8, Folder 116)
  - Peaks, Lenora. Durham. Minister. 1998 July 28 (Box 8, Folder 117)
  - Mercy Hospital. Moore, Hazel. Wilson. 1996 July 31 (Box 8, Folder 118)
  - Mercy Hospital. Exum, Roxanna. Wilson. Nurse. 1996 Aug. 1 (Box 8, Folder 119)
  - Mercy Hospital. Exum, Roxanna. Wilson. Nurse. 1996 July 18 (Box 8, Folder 120)
  - Mercy Hospital. Corbett, Fannie. Wilson. 1996 July 30 (Box 8, Folder 121)
  - Mercy Hospital. Byumn, Lucy. Wilson. Nursing Assistant. 1996 Aug. 1 (Box 8, Folder 122)
  - Mercy Hospital. Bynum, Gladys. Wilson. 1996 July 25 (Box 9, Folder 123)
  - Mercy Hospital. Tucker, Mary. Wilson 1996 July 29 (Box 9, Folder 124)
  - Mercy Hospital. Barnes, Ivey. Wilson. Accountant. 1996 July 31 (Box 9, Folder 125)
  - Mercy Hospital. Barnes, Annie. Wilson. 1996 July 30 (Box 9, Folder 126)
  - Summerton, S.C. Pearson, Viola, Manning. 1997 July 7 (Box 9, Folder 127)
  - Summer Training. Johnson, Betty. Durham. City Planner. 1997 June 9 (Box 9, Folder 128)
  - Mercy Hospital. Bynum, Frances. Wilson. Nurse. 1996 July 31 (Box 9, Folder 129)
  - Behind the Veil. Richburg, Josie. Summerton, S.C. Maid, Cook. 1996 June 28 (Box 9, Folder 130)
  - Wilson. Sharpe, Mark. Wilson Farmer. 1997 July 9 (Box 9, Folder 131)
  - Wilson. Tillary, Irene. Elm City. 1997 July 21 (Box 9, Folder 132)
  - McDonald, Annie. Summerton, S.C. Campbell's Soup Employee. 1996 July 1 (Box 10, Folder 133)
  - DeLaine, Lula. Manning. 1996 July 7 (Box 10, Folder 134)
  - Lewis, Webb. Summerton, S.C. Farmer, Sanitation Worker. 1996 July 7 (Box 10, Folder 135)
  - Adger, Janie. Summerton, S.C. 1996 June 27 (Box 10, Folder 136)
  - Pearson, Louise. Manning. Teacher. 1996 July 10 (Box 10, Folder 137)
  - Wilson. Jones, Marvin. Wilson. 1997 July 10 (Box 10, Folder 138)
  - Lawson, Henry. Summerton, S.C. Farmer, Truck Driver, Self-Employed. 1996 July 3 (Box 10, Folder 139)
  - Behind the Veil. Guess, Clinton. Pinewood. Bus Driver. 1995 June 30 (Box 10, Folder 140)
  - Summerton, S.C. Blackwell, Hattie. Summerton, S.C. 1997 July 14 (Box 11, Folder 141)
  - Mercy Hospital. Townsend, Marcus. Wilson. 1996 July 25 (Box 11, Folder 142)
  - Mercy Hospital. Davis, Otha. Wilson. 1996 July 24 (Box 11, Folder 143)
  - Behind the Veil. Boyd, Roosevelt. Pinewood. Minister. 1995 July 9 (Box 11, Folder 144)
  - Behind the Veil. Caldwell, Betty. Manning. Teacher, Administrator. 1995 July 12 (Box 11, Folder 145)
  - Behind the Veil. Richburg, Joseph. Summerton, S.C. Barber. 1995 July 7 (Box 11, Folder 146)
  - Behind the Veil. Dingle, Martha. Summerton, S.C. Housekeeper, Dry Cleaning. 1995 June 30 (Box 11, Folder 147)
  - Behind the Veil. Butler, Broadus. Summerton, S.C. Teacher, Principal, Superintendent. 1995 July 5 (Box 11, Folder 148)
  - Behind the Veil. Spann, Harold. Pinewood. 1995 July 9 (Box 11, Folder 149)
  - Mercy Hospital. Whitted, Bessie. Wilson. Nurse. 1996 July 29 (Box 11, Folder 150)
  - Mercy Hospital. Dickerson, Thelma. Wilson. Nurses Aid. 1996 Aug. 1 (Box 11, Folder 151)
  - Mercy Hospital. Johnson, Thelma. Wilson. Nurse. 1996 July 29 (Box 12, Folder 152)
  - Mercy Hospital. Murrain, Gwen. Wilson. Nurse. 1996 Aug. 1 (Box 12, Folder 153)
  - Mercy Hospital. Barnes, Ruth. Wilson. 1996 July 29 (Box 12, Folder 154)
  - Mercy Hospital. Barnes, Katie. Wilson. Patient Representative. 1996 Aug. 1 (Box 12, Folder 155)
  - Mercy Hospital. Sullivan, Jean. Wilson. 1996 July 26 (Box 12, Folder 156)
  - Summerton, S.C. Gaters, F. Mt. Pleasant. Lawyer. 1997 July 17 (Box 12, Folder 157)
  - Crest Street. Holman, Sheila. Durham. 1997 July 10 (Box 12, Folder 158)
  - Crest Street. Pratt, Nathaniel. Durham. 1997 July 16 (Box 12, Folder 159)
  - Summerton, S.C. Patterson, Shirley. Summerton, S.C. 1997 July 1 (Box 12, Folder 160)
  - Summerton, S.C. Billups, Annie. Summerton, S.C. Accounts Payable Clerk. 1996 July 6 (Box 12, Folder 161)